<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>AHRS for Stratux</title>
    <link>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on AHRS for Stratux</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 14:38:08 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://westphae.github.io/stratux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 14:38:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/collaboration/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://westphae.github.io/stratux/img/contact-bg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;splash&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;issues&#34;&gt;Issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit any issues on my fork&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/westphae/stratux/issues&#34;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; area.
Every flight creates a file in /var/log/sensors_YYYYMMDD_HHMMSS.csv, which you can upload.
It might also be helpful to upload /var/log/stratux.log in certain situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback&#34;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please contact me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://stratuxadsb.slack.com/team/bonanzaeric&#34;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, either with a direct message
or in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://stratuxadsb.slack.com/messages/ahrs/&#34;&gt;ahrs&lt;/a&gt; channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not on Slack, you can use one of the links at left.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Stratux AHRS image for beta testers</title>
      <link>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/howto/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 14:41:29 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/howto/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I am excited to finally offer a Stratux image for anyone who would like to help beta test my initial AHRS solution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this image, in addition to the normal Stratux requriements, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to connect an MPU-9250 sensor to your Stratux.
The OpenFlightSolutions AHRS board is a great choice.
You can also use a RY836AI (tested), a SparkFun MPU-9250 breakout board (tested), or your own home brew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code also has a driver for the BMP280, which also exists on both the OpenFlightSolutions AHRS board and the RY836AI.
If you have one of these boards or a separate dev board, the pressure altitude and rate of climb will be used in the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Plan for AHRS Development</title>
      <link>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 16:40:25 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/plan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on AHRS for about 9 months now.
My original approach was to use an Extended Kalman Filter.
This proved to be a bit more difficult than I&amp;rsquo;d expected!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to get something working and build a framework to integrate it into the Stratux code, I instead took an approach I call the &amp;ldquo;SimpleAHRS&amp;rdquo; algorithm.
Like @AvSquirrel&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;GPS-only&amp;rdquo; approach, its foundation is an attitude estimate based on GPS.
Then the sensors are used to &amp;ldquo;tweak&amp;rdquo; the calculated attitude.
This allows it to respond to changes in attitude in realtime and to account somewhat for uncoordinated maneuvers.
However, it does still have a few deficiencies.
Mainly, it cannot get pitch quite right.
Also, uncoordinated maneuvers that persist for more than a few seconds will begin to display incorrectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A true AHRS system should be based on a Kalman filter (or derivative) fusion of sensors:
* Gyros
* Accelerations
* Magnetometer
* GPS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even better is ADAHARS: Air Data And Heading Reference System.  This would also incorporate:
* Airspeed
* Barometer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current approach uses GPS, gyro and barometer.
The next iteration will use GPS, gyro, accelerometer, barometer, and possibly magnetometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematical details of the algorithms, simulations, etc. are or will be available in the documentation for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/westphae/goflying&#34;&gt;https://github.com/westphae/goflying&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AHRS for Stratux</title>
      <link>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 22:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://westphae.github.io/stratux/img/intro-bg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;splash&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/westphae/stratux&#34;&gt;fork&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cyoung/stratux&#34;&gt;Stratux&lt;/a&gt; project.
It is mainly intended to provide AHRS (Attitude Heading and Reference System) features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created this site to help beta testers to download, install, and use this fork,
and to provide me feedback and/or collaborate on its further development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AHRS support requires writing drivers for sensor hardware, Kalman filter and other approaches
for determining attitude from sensor input, and software simulators for testing these algorithms.
The main code for AHRS is in a separate GitHub repository of mine, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/westphae/goflying&#34;&gt;https://github.com/westphae/goflying&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fork incorporates minimal changes into the stratux code to integrate the AHRS code from the goflying library.
Hopefully it will eventually be merged into the main stratux project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>