<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plans on AHRS for Stratux</title>
    <link>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/plan/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Plans on AHRS for Stratux</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 16:40:25 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://westphae.github.io/stratux/plan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My Plan for AHRS Development</title>
      <link>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 16:40:25 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://westphae.github.io/stratux/plan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on AHRS for about 9 months now.
My original approach was to use an Extended Kalman Filter.
This proved to be a bit more difficult than I&amp;rsquo;d expected!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to get something working and build a framework to integrate it into the Stratux code, I instead took an approach I call the &amp;ldquo;SimpleAHRS&amp;rdquo; algorithm.
Like @AvSquirrel&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;GPS-only&amp;rdquo; approach, its foundation is an attitude estimate based on GPS.
Then the sensors are used to &amp;ldquo;tweak&amp;rdquo; the calculated attitude.
This allows it to respond to changes in attitude in realtime and to account somewhat for uncoordinated maneuvers.
However, it does still have a few deficiencies.
Mainly, it cannot get pitch quite right.
Also, uncoordinated maneuvers that persist for more than a few seconds will begin to display incorrectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A true AHRS system should be based on a Kalman filter (or derivative) fusion of sensors:
* Gyros
* Accelerations
* Magnetometer
* GPS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even better is ADAHARS: Air Data And Heading Reference System.  This would also incorporate:
* Airspeed
* Barometer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current approach uses GPS, gyro and barometer.
The next iteration will use GPS, gyro, accelerometer, barometer, and possibly magnetometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematical details of the algorithms, simulations, etc. are or will be available in the documentation for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/westphae/goflying&#34;&gt;https://github.com/westphae/goflying&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>